hi Tyler stalman now I think most people
at this point realize that Final Cut Pro
is really fast and generally pretty easy
to use but I think it's led to this
common misconception that it's only for
simple projects if you want something
more complicated you've got to use more
complicated software and I'm here to
bust that myth just a little bit we're
going to go into some slightly more
advanced tips and tricks so if you're
already familiar with Final Cut this
will take you a step further and if you
don't know the basics yet I got a
playlist all about that let's get
started first off speed ramps so this is
a pretty common thing these days where
you just suddenly speed up footage and
in this drone shot you can see that we
have like a lot of motion at the
beginning when we're flying over Anya
here but then gradually it just goes
into the same thing for a while so what
I want to happen is that all of a sudden
it ramps up and this part plays really
quickly the way I used to do this the
wrong way is that you might cut
something here click on it and then go
to this little speed tool and you could
say fast and it may play plays it 20
times and that would you know give us
our basic effect where suddenly it
speeds up but there is a much better way
so first we're going to find the moment
in the video we want to transition and
you know traditionally you might press
command B which would cut it and then
you could select each side of the clip
change those but instead we're going to
press shift B and it's sort of like a
blade tool that only affects the speed
and now we can go to the drop down and
say this is going to be 20 times faster
and we can make the speed ramp more
gradual now let's play
it all right that's just about what I
wanted now I'm going to make a few
tweaks here first of all I want to ramp
into the speed up a little more so it's
more gradual and then also I got the
point slightly wrong that's not where I
want it to happen I want to happen just
as her head disappears so what I can do
instead is double click on this
transition Point edit the source frame
and just move it over till it's exactly
where I want it and there we go I got a
nice clean speed ramp all contained
within one clip here's another tip if
you want to customize your commands I'd
recommend giving something to a commonly
used speed ramp so I'm going search for
Speed and I'm going to look for fast
eight times and I give that shift eight
as the shortcut and now if I select a
clip that will instantly jump it down to
being that speed so if you're somebody
like me that speed ramps all the time
you can do it really quickly also got a
handy shortcut I've been using a lot for
transitions so a visual transition I
could select between two clips and press
command T and it will add the default
which is just a basic dissolve from one
clip to another I don't use dissolve
transitions very often so I can actually
go in and one that I do use a bit is
slide so I can right click it and say
make default now if I press command T
this is my new default transition I
would not use it like that but I do use
it especially for screen recordings but
I can tell you're still not excited cuz
you are a classy editor and you wouldn't
use a Cheesy transition like that so
we're going to jump over to another kind
of video this is where there's a lot
more speaking and a roll and what I do
use all the time is I'd select two clips
instead of command press option T and
that gives me if I zoom way in here a
very subtle audio transition so that it
Blends smoothly from One Clip to the
other you can modify that if you want
make it shorter but this is extremely
helpful for talking head videos or
especially things like podcasts where
you want to blend together a cut so you
can't hear the cut I use option T all
the time but there's another way to fix
those cheesy transitions you could go
get some nice transitions so motion VFX
sponsor of this video has some beautiful
ones so over here I've got some already
installed in my M film mat these are
some film transitions I'm just going to
like drop a few on let's watch them back
to
back boom
what else we got o a film
burn nice and if it's not exactly to
your liking there's a lot of different
controls you can change about it so
maybe let's crank up the saturation of
those light leaks may you want to turn
off the scratches change the way that
the blur is visible and let's take a
look cool but that's just one of so many
things the motion bfx can do I want to
show you some more of the film emulation
stuff cuz I really like it so if I go
into my effects we'll take a look at M16
mm and this is basically just film
emulation full vintage Vibes and I'm
just going to put a different one on
each clip let's like watch them all back
to back so now I've taken my drone home
videos and Hyper stylize them in just a
few seconds and like I say this is just
the drag and drop version but you can
get in there and customize it all you
want and there's a whole bunch of motion
bfx stuff that I've been using in my
videos for over 5 years now you've seen
them before here this is a good example
this Arrow this humble simple arrow has
shown up so many times and the reason I
like it is cuz I can really customize it
so I can turn off these rough edges
which usually I do and I can move it
around and kind of create different
shapes with it so it can be curving this
way and then I rotate it now it's
pointing over here then I going to move
the whole thing over here and I can make
it yellow and I can make it thicker all
this flexibility means that this one
Arrow plugin I've used over and over and
it animates into place and it can
animate out but it's just a really
versatile tool that I keep coming back
to motion B effect loves Final Cut
almost as much as I do they have a team
of highly skilled in-house developers
that are constantly working on infinite
different plugins that do everything you
can imagine some of them are clean and
simple titles used by tons of your
favorite YouTubers some are professional
and corporate Styles so you can use them
for your clients and like the film
emulation I was showing you some of it
is just super stylish and meant to make
your video look cool so whatever project
you're working on in Final Cut motion V
effects will have something for you
check out the link in the description
thanks to motion VFX let's keep going
and for this next tip I'm going to use
some of their cinematic titles let's try
an unexpected Letter Okay so this Title
Here is using some fonts by default
let's check out what they are it's
something called lto light now I have a
YouTube channel and if you have any sort
of Channel or client you continually
work for I highly recommend that you go
into your fonts and choose whatever
their standard font is and make it into
a preset so now I just click and
instantly it's using my brand of font
which is the one that I always use this
video is not about an unexpected letter
it's about an unexpected final cut
tutorial so this can come in handy all
the time let's start again I'm going to
actually delete that one and use a
default title there's a shortcut for
that it is control T we're using every
single T shortcut today and there you go
by default there's just text in the
middle of the screen I'm going change
what it says now my font is
beas BAS NOA I'm select I don't know
what's kind of a common beginning font
size and there's other parameters here
you can do a default color I mean maybe
I'll make one for yellow cuz I I do use
that specific color of yellow pretty
often uh I usually have a little bit of
higher tracking let's say four and now
up here I want to save all formats and
appearance attributes I'm going to name
it how about yellow bass and there it is
it is stored along with all the others
that I regularly go to in all my final
cut videos I think one of the most
useful tips is always showing you to put
all of your a roll into one compound
clip so now I'm going to take that
another step further so here I've got a
whole bunch of stuff that is all a-roll
and as usual press option G and now it
is inside of a compound clip so if I
make some edits and then I go inside the
clip and do something to all of them
like let's say add one of my transform
Luts uh this one Cog 2 all of a sudden
everything looks great all throughout
and then I go back to my edits and it's
there now that was just one example of
the power of a compound clip I'll show
you another way I use it so here's some
a-roll of me talking blah blah blah if I
make the timeline bigger I can see there
is something going on here this this is
noise this is just background
ambient like hiss or whatever let's
listen to
it it's just ambient room tone it's in
every audio file but I like to clean it
up as much as possible so here's how I
do it the only way I found that really
preserves all the audio quality now I'm
sure somebody will point out this is
built into Final Cut you can click noise
removal this does not sound very good
you can hear it processing the spoken
word and I don't recommend using it
first up we're going to press option G
turn this into a compound clip and then
go ins inside it now I need to create a
wave file and this is because I need to
do some of this processing externally
none of it can be done in real time well
enough in Final Cut so I do need to use
outside tools so I'm going to right
click reveal this clip in the browser
now I'm going to reveal it in my finder
and there it is then I open up
compressor which is the sister software
to Final Cut Pro drag that clip into
compressor I go to my audio formats
select wave drag it to the clip and hit
start batch now you don't have to use
compress to do this anything that'll
take a video file and extract a high
quality wave file from it will do the
same thing and now you can take that
wave and use any professional audio
software you have and do a highquality
pass of noise removal I like isotope so
I open up RX8 let's zoom into an area
that is nothing but noise that is the uh
orange part if you can't tell there I'm
going to go to Voice D noise and
importantly click learn this is the
difference is live processing is much
harder and if you learn a section of the
existing noise and then remove it from
everything else it sounds so much better
my reduction amount usually is between
like 8 and maybe 12 let's go to 10 and
you can see the before and after that
orange the noise is really cleaned up
let's hear before and after so
before and
after now there's all sorts of different
types of noise removal that I can do but
again always learning it and rendering
it into the file has higher quality it's
like video game graphics compared to
pre-rendered you can always pre-render
at a higher quality level great now I
just save that wave file all right now
we're back in Final Cut I'm just going
to grab that wave drag it into my
compound clip make sure that it aligns
with the beginning mute the original so
now the audio is coming from the wave
file instead of from the video file and
when I go back to my timeline it just
looks like a normal clip I can't really
tell what happened this can also speed
up Final Cut CU if you have a bunch of
different audio filters running in real
time it can slow down your software but
let's look at another way that compound
Clips can help and that's with
multitrack so let's open up the multicam
and this has three different angles the
first one is just me talking the next
one is my screen recording and after
that is both and they need to be in sync
here and they need to follow through
with any changes I make for example if I
change the color grading on me it needs
to show up in the a-roll and in the
mixed a-roll and screen recording angle
so I'll show you how to do it this clip
and this one are both already compound
Clips cuz that's what we do here then
I'll create a new angle I'll call it
both Clips I don't know copy my screen
recording line it up with the beginning
cuz they have to be in sync and select
both clips and paste it in there all
right now we're going to need to go
deeper an extra level of nesting so I'm
going to select that and create a new
compound clip out bit I'm going to call
it both again and then I'm going to
select my a
roll go inside that both compound clip
paste my a roll and now I have both of
them in sync on one end angle and all I
have to do is lay them out so I don't
know I could do things like make it
smaller uh maybe here I'll do the
simplest version I'll just put me in the
corner that's something you can do for
you know basic uh tutorial videos I'm
going to crop the left crop the right
and good enough for now now if you're
not already impressed by compound Clips
there's one more thing you can do with
it and I do it at the end of most videos
so as we're watching you can keep an eye
on the right here and see our levels
they're actually they're actually pretty
good I messed this pretty well but often
you'll find an imbalance between your
levels let's say you're mixing different
sources and some of them are turned down
using the volume slider and they're not
completely even between them you do the
best you can but at the end I go and I
say command a select all of my clips and
then again press option G which creates
a compound clip I call it audio master
and now there's just one track for
everything if I double click it it's
like my regular Video Edit it's all
inside of there but if I go back I have
one compound clip with everything and on
top of that I can add a limiter which is
usually what I do just to kind of boost
the volume I turn up the gain a bit and
the nice thing about a limiter instead
of just using volume is that there is a
limit on the output so if I start
playing it here if I turn this up too
high you can see it never Clips it never
hits the red if I turned up the output
level eventually it could start clipping
we don't want it to clip so basically a
limiter is a more or less safe way to to
increase your volume you can't go too
far with it but it does help you get
more of a consistent output and it's all
thanks to these compound clips now my
final tip this is for the YouTubers out
there it was in the podcast recently but
I think I haven't had it in any of my
final cut tutorials it comes from
Patrick Tomaso I had them on the show so
of course he gave it to us but it's very
simple when you're uploading video go to
share export file and if you're like me
most of the time I select video and
audio and I go with h264 it creates a
big beefy h264 file that looks really
good and is you know good to hold on to
I'd rather archive that than what we're
about to do but instead you go to format
Apple devices make sure that you're in
your full resolution I usually use
better quality in code and if you use
these export settings your processing
time on YouTube can be cut from several
hours down to several minutes it's
actually like magic I have no idea why
it does this but it completely changes
how long you can wait for your video to
be done so I sure hope something in this
video was helpful and I hope you go
check out motion via facts again link is
in the description and I'll see you guys
in the next video